<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
/*
 *                  Teolenn development code
 *
 * This code may be freely distributed and modified under the
 * terms of the GNU General Public License version 2 or later. This
 * should be distributed with the code. If you do not have a copy,
 * see:
 *
 *      http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.txt
 *
 * Copyright for this code is held jointly by the microarray platform
 * of the École Normale Supérieure and the individual authors.
 * These should be listed in @author doc comments.
 *
 * For more information on the Teolenn project and its aims,
 * or to join the Teolenn Google group, visit the home page
 * at:
 *
 *      http://www.transcriptome.ens.fr/teolenn
 *
 */
-->
<document>

<properties>
  <title>The design file</title>
  <author email="jourdren@biologie.ens.fr">Laurent Jourdren</author>
</properties>

<body>
    
  <section name="The design file">
  
  <p>The design file (usually named as <code>design.xml</code>) is the file where all the parameters of a design will be set. This file use the XML syntax and is divided in 8 sections : </p>
  
  <ul>
    <li>The <a href="design-global.html">global parameters</a>. Set the main parameter of the design (length of oligonucleotides, path to the files...).</li>
    <li>The <a href="design-constants.html">constant section</a>. This section allow to set constants that will be used in the whole design file. This section is optional.</li>
    <li>The <a href="design-sequencescreator.html">sequencefilters</a> section. This section enable or not the creation of all the oligonucleotides. This section is also optional.</li>
    <li>The <a href="design-sequencesfilters.html">sequencefilters</a> section. This section define the filters on all the oligonucleotides generated.</li>
    <li>The <a href="design-measurements.html">measurements section</a>. This section define the measurement to compute on the filtered oligonucleotides.</li>
    <li>The <a href="design-measurementfilters.html">measurementfilters</a> section. This section define the filters based on measurements to remove oligonucleotides.</li>
    <li>The <a href="design-select.html">select section</a>. This part of the file set the parameters to select the best oligonucleotide for each window.</li>
    <li>The <a href="design-outputs.html">outputs section</a>. This last part of the file set the parameters of the output(s) of selected oligonucleotides. If this section is absent, the default output will be used.</li>
  </ul>
  
  <p>The following source show the structure of a typical <code>design.xml</code> file:</p>
  
  <source>
&lt;design&gt;
    &lt;formatversion&gt;1.1&lt;/formatversion&gt;
    
    &lt;startposition&gt;0&lt;/startposition&gt;
    &lt;oligolength&gt;60&lt;/oligolength&gt;

    &lt;genomefile&gt;Ca21_chromosomes2.fasta&lt;/genomefile&gt;
    &lt;genomemaskedfile&gt;Ca21_chromosomes2.fasta.allmasked&lt;/genomemaskedfile&gt;
    &lt;outputdir&gt;/home/jourdren/tmp/candida_design&lt;/outputdir&gt;
    
    &lt;constants&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/constants&gt;

    &lt;sequencecreator/&gt;

    &lt;sequencefilters&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/sequencfilters&gt;
    
    &lt;measurements&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/measurements&gt;
    
    &lt;measurementfilters&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/measurementfilters&gt;
    
    &lt;select&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/select&gt;
    
    &lt;outputs&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/outputs&gt;
&lt;/design&gt;</source>

	<subsection name="Skip steps">
	
	<p>All the phases from sequences creation to selection of the best oligonucleotides can be skipped. To skip a phase set the skip attribute to true in the phase tag. As an example the following fragment of design file will skip the selection phase:</p>
	<source>
    &lt;select skip="true"&gt;
    ...
    &lt;/select&gt;</source>
	</subsection>

  	<subsection name="Built-in variables">
  	
  		<p>In parameters sections of the design file, you can use the 
  		following built-in variables as values for parameters:</p>
  		
  		<ul>
  			<li><b>${startPosition}</b>: Contains the way the first position of the sequence is referred to. Can take value 0 or 1.</li>
  			<li><b>${genomefile}</b>: Contains the path to the genome file.</li>
  			<li><b>${genomemaskedfile}</b>: Contains the path to the genome masked file.</li>
  			<li><b>${outputdir}</b>: Contains the path to the output directory.</li>
  			<li><b>${oligolenght}</b>: Contains the length of the oligonucleotides.</li>  			
  		</ul>
  		
  	
  	</subsection>
  
  </section>
  
  
</body>
</document>