<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
/*
 *                  Teolenn development code
 *
 * This code may be freely distributed and modified under the
 * terms of the GNU General Public License version 2 or later. This
 * should be distributed with the code. If you do not have a copy,
 * see:
 *
 *      http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-2.0.txt
 *
 * Copyright for this code is held jointly by the microarray platform
 * of the École Normale Supérieure and the individual authors.
 * These should be listed in @author doc comments.
 *
 * For more information on the Teolenn project and its aims,
 * or to join the Teolenn Google group, visit the home page
 * at:
 *
 *      http://www.transcriptome.ens.fr/teolenn
 *
 */
-->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <author email="jourdren@biologie.ens.fr">Laurent Jourdren</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
  
    <section name="How to run a design with Teolenn">
    
        <subsection  name="Requirements">
        
        <p>To run Teolenn you need:</p>
        
        <ul>
            <li>A computer that can execute 
            Teolenn (see <a href="download.html#">installation requirements</a> for more informations).</li>
            <li><a href="download.html">Download Teolenn</a> and <a href="installing.html">install it</a>.</li>
            <li>The sequence of the genome you want use for the design.
                <ul>
                    <li>This genome must be in one file using the Fasta format.</li>
                    <li>The header of each chromosome or scaffold must be simple (short as possible, without punctuation marks or other symbols). 
                        <source>
>chromosome_1
TATATAAAAACCTTTACTACTTTTACTATTATTATTACCTTATTATATAGTTATAATTAACTTCCTTTTA
GCACTACTATTAATAAATAATAAATATAATATACTACTAATTACTATAAATAAATTTAGTAAAAAGGTAA
TTCTAAAACTAGTTAAAAAAACTAATATAGCCTTAAAAATAGCTAATAAGCTAGTAGCAAGACTTTTAAA
...</source></li>
                </ul>
            </li>
            <li>The sequence of the masked genome if you want use the complexity measurement.
                <ul>
                    <li>This genome must be in one file using the Fasta format.</li>
                    <li>The header of each chromosome or scaffold must be simple (short as possible, without punctuation marks or other symbols).</li>
                    <li>The name of the header of each chromosome must be the same for genome file and genome masked file.</li>
                </ul>
            
            </li>
        </ul>
        
        
        </subsection>
        
        
        
        <subsection name="Non standard Installation">
        
        <p><a href="http://soap.genomics.org.cn">Soap</a> and 
        <a href="http://genometools.org/">genometools</a> can be installed 
        manualy. This is mandatory if the executable is not built-in in Teolenn. The following versions of soap and genometools are embedded in Toelenn:</p>
        
        <table>
            <tr><th>Tool</th><th>Version</th><th>OS</th><th>Arch</th><th>Comment</th></tr>
            <tr><td>soap</td><td>1.11</td><td>Linux 2.6.8+</td><td>i386</td><td></td></tr>
            <tr><td>soap</td><td>1.11</td><td>Linux 2.6.8+</td><td>x86_64</td><td></td></tr>
	    <tr><td>soap</td><td>1.11</td><td>Mac OS 10.5+</td><td>i386</td><td></td></tr>
	    <tr><td>soap</td><td>1.11</td><td>Mac OS 10.5+</td><td>x86_64</td><td>This the i386 that is embedded because it was impossible to compile genometools
            as a static executable for this architecture.</td></tr>
            <tr><td>genometools</td><td>1.2.0</td><td>Linux 2.4.1+</td><td>i386</td><td></td></tr>
            <tr><td>genometools</td><td>1.2.0</td><td>Linux 2.4.1+</td><td>x86_64</td><td>
            This the i386 that is embedded because it was impossible to compile genometools 
            as a static executable for this architecture. IA32 compatibility 
            libraries are needed.</td></tr>
	    <tr><td>genometools</td><td>1.2.0</td><td>Mac OS 10.5+</td><td>i386</td><td></td></tr>
	    <tr><td>genometools</td><td>1.2.0</td><td>Mac OS 10.5+</td><td>x86_64</td><td>This the i386 that is embedded because it was impossible to compile genometools
            as a static executable for this architecture.</td></tr>
        </table>
        
        
        </subsection>
    
        <subsection name="The design file">
        
            <p>The design file is the core element of a design using Teolenn. It 
            contains the filters to apply on generated sequences, the measurements
            to compute, the filters on measurements and the selection parameters.
            The design file is an XML file (see 
            <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XML">Wikipedia article</a> for 
            more information about XML). This file allow Teolenn to be a very flexible 
            design tool. As the design file is the central part of Teolenn you must 
            read carefully the <a href="design.html">design file section</a> of the
            documentation.</p>
            
            <p>You can also use the <a href="./design-thricoderna-reesei.xml"><i>Trichoderma 
            reesei</i> design file</a> as a model for your design.
            Sequence and sequence masked of <i>Trichoderma reesei</i> 
            are available on the <a href="http://genome.jgi-psf.org/Trire2/Trire2.download.html">website of the JGI</a>. <b>Don't forget in 
            this design that the parameters are specific to <i>Trichoderma reesei</i> and
            <u>need to be adapted for your design</u>.</b></p> 
            
        </subsection>
    
    
        <subsection name="The Teolenn process">
        
            <p>There are 4 steps in the Teolenn process to select probes:</p>
        
           <ol>
            <li>Generate all oligonucleotides sequences for the genome and the 
            genome masked (create one file per chromosome, the extension of 
            this files are "<b>.oligo</b>" and "<b>.masked</b>" files).
            Filter oligonucleotides sequences (one file per chromosome, the extension of 
            this files are "<b>.oligo.filtered</b>" and "<b>.masked.filtered</b>" files)</li>
            <li>Compute measurements (create the <b>oligo.mes</b> file)</li>
            <li>Filter measurements (create the <b>filtered.mes</b> and the <b>filtered.stat</b> file)</li>
            <li>Compute the selection of the oligonucleotides (create the <b>select.mes</b> file). In this final step:
                <ol>
                    <li>For each measurement and oligonucleotide, Teolenn compute a score using the measurement value and 
                    sometimes one or more statistical parameters (defined in the parameters values of the measurements in the
                    select section of the design file). A score is a float value between 0 and 1 whereas a measurement 
                    value can have any type and value (negative, string...).</li>
               
                    <li>Apply a weight on each measurement score to get a global score for an oligonucleotide.</li>
                    <li>Choose the oligonucleotide with the best score in each selection window.</li>
                </ol>           
            </li>
           </ol>
                
            <p>As there is the need of statistical data for the last step of 
            the process, Teolenn must be launched two times. One to get the statistical 
            data and one to get the selected oligonucleotides. You can skip 
            the 4 firsts steps in the second run using the <b>skip</b> attribute 
            in the design file (see the <a href="design.html">design file section</a> 
            of the documentation for more information).</p>   
        
        </subsection>
    
    </section>
  
  </body>
</document>
